<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The crie of blood, or, A confutation of those thirteene reasons of the felicers at Westminster for the maintenance of their illegall capias for debt by which is discovered the great benefit and freedome that will accrew to the people of the common wealth by the reformation of that destructive law / by Joht [sic] Jones of Neyath in Com. Brecon, gent.</title>
            <author>Jones, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J964B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13535527</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13535527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100047</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47058)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100047)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1551:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The crie of blood, or, A confutation of those thirteene reasons of the felicers at Westminster for the maintenance of their illegall capias for debt by which is discovered the great benefit and freedome that will accrew to the people of the common wealth by the reformation of that destructive law / by Joht [sic] Jones of Neyath in Com. Brecon, gent.</title>
                  <author>Jones, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Matthewes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show- through, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard Law School Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Debt, Imprisonment for --  England.</term>
               <term>Debtor and creditor.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CRIE OF BLOOD: OR, A Confutation of thoſe Thirteene Reaſons of the <hi>Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their illegall <hi>Capias</hi> for Debt.</p>
            <p>By which is diſcovered the great benefit and freedome that will accrew to the people of the Common wealth by the reformation of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Law.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 11.46.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Woe unto you Lawyars, for ye lade men with burthens grievous to be borne, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Joht Jones</hi> of <hi>Neyath in Com Brecon.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Matthewes,</hi> at the <hi>Cock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:2"/>
            <head>To his Excellence <hi>OLIVER CROMWEL,</hi> Lord General of the puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Armie of the PARLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Renowned Sir!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, ſo are your cares, troubles, ſufferings, actions and endeavors all
<pb facs="tcp:100047:3"/>general, for the general good of this Nation in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral: Nor is the caſe and number of the Priſoners for Debt in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> for whom you have been, and are a ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous, although yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſperous mediator to the Houſ of Parlament ſo ſmall a particular, but that as the prudent King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who accompted his bodie but ſmall to the reſt of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, and knew
<pb facs="tcp:100047:3"/>it to be mortal, deſired to be dailie remembred he was mortal, to the end he ſhould not more glorie in what he had well done, than perſevere in well-doing, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his wel-begun enterpriſes; that ſo he might immortaliſe his fame, and illuſtrate the faculties of his immortal virtues, that poſteritie might ſpeak of him, not like <hi>Pythagoriſts</hi> of their maſter, <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> but <hi>ipſe
<pb facs="tcp:100047:4"/>fecit;</hi> nay more, <hi>ipſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecit.</hi> I hope likewiſe your Excellence will not be offended with me one of the heartieſt, though of the meaneſt of your Honors wel-wiſhers, to mind you of the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected miſeries of the ſaid priſoners now, more then ever, likelier to be continued and increaſed then relieved, or abated by the generation of Lawyers overſwaying the mildeneſs of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:100047:4"/>Parlament Members that have long promiſed you to be merciful to ſuch Priſoners, and to haſten their enlargement out of their wrongful impriſonments; which, if you ſee performed, as hereafter is deſired, wil be an action of no leſs Divinitie then Charitie, and no leſſe profit then Honour to your ſelf in particular, and the Common-wealth in general. The Officers in
<pb facs="tcp:100047:5"/>Law have latelie preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Parlament with 13. Reaſons or the maintenance of Arreſts and Impriſonment for Debt, contrarie to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> as I have eftſoons proved elſwhere, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant even to Reaſon it ſelf, as I have here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing farther declared in anſwer to their ſaid Reaſons in the Priſoner's behalf; in which, and whoſe names I likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:100047:5"/>humbly dedicate the ſame to your Honor, with a copie of the ſaid Reaſons hereunto firſt annexed as it came to my hands, and next an anſwer to their preamble: and afterward particular an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to their particular Ratiocinations: and laſtly, the Priſoner's humble Petition to your Honor; all which I could not have readie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Colonel <hi>Pride's</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture (whom God
<pb facs="tcp:100047:6"/>proſper in your Service, and the Common-wealth's, whoſe welfare hee preferreth above all worldlie ends) but have now preſumed to ſend them unto you; beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Honor that your Lieutenant General, Colonel <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> (a man of no leſs worth then eminence) or ſome other like publik ſpirit may act in this matter, and others of the like nature in your Honor's
<pb facs="tcp:100047:6"/>abſence according to your directions, and the people's neceſsitie from time to time, that no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie bee loſt, and more lives of Priſoners bee ſaved, and your care thereof to the uttermoſt expeſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord Preſident of the Council of State, and Col.</hi> Martin <hi>are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to bee no leſs willing then able to procure ſuch a Commiſſion as the Petitioners deſire, and Law would afford, if your Honor would be pleaſed to write to them, which I humblie ſubmit to your Honor's conſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So wiſheth your dailie Orator, <hi>John Jones.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:7"/>
            <head>REASONS for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the proceſs of Arreſts, for the good of the Common-wealth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He proceedings by waie of Arreſt at the King's Suit; and in all actions that were <hi>Quare vi &amp; Armis,</hi> between the ſubjects, are as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as the Common Law of this Land; but the proceſs for the people in other Actions, was Summons, Attachment, and diſtreſs, which Courſ, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Debts, did prove dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie,
<pb facs="tcp:100047:8"/>and manie times fruitleſs, to the great hinderance of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, and other Commerce in this Nation; and therefore former Parliaments did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide as appears by divers Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes) the writ of <hi>Capias</hi> to an Arreſt as a full remedie, and moſt neceſſarie for this Common-wealth. <hi>3 Rep. 12.</hi> Sir <hi>Will Herbert's Caſe. 52 Hen. 3. in Accomp. 1267.25 Edw. 3. c. 17. An. Dom. 1350.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Becauſ attaching the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth ſecure the Petitioner's debt, either by preſent paiment, or cauſing other ſatisfaction, which the proceedings by ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons do not; and as a man will give all for his life, ſo hee will do much for his libertie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:8"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> When men are deteined upon the Arreſt (which is but ſeldom, for few are arreſted in compariſon, and then) it is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narilie but for a ſhort time, until they have given ſecuritie to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Action, or ſom warrant to appear.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> If men may not proceed by Arreſt, it will much hinder Trade, and other dealings; for men will not adventure to truſt, where there is much libertie for the debtor to ſtand out; and Merchants, and Tradeſ men manie times look upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as the beſt ſecuritie, and the remedie by Arreſt, the ſpeediest to gain their debts; without which Trade will neceſſarilie decaie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:9"/>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The proceſs to Arreſt, doth end moſt ſuits before the Perſon bee attached, and before appearance, as experience doth ſhew; for when men will not regard a ſummons, they will take courſ before they will ſuffer an Arreſt, <hi>52 Hen. 3. cap. 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>5.</hi> Men will take occaſion from the ſummons (as formerlie they have done) to be gon from one Countrie to another, and to make awaie their eſtates, and though the Plaintiff know it, yet hee cannot help himſelf, which the Arreſt doth prevent: And the Law-makers of this Land have ever held it more reaſonable to provide for the ſatisfaction of the Creditor, then the libertie of the Debtor.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:9"/>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6. England</hi> is an Iſland compaſſed with manie Port Towns, where there are manie Merchants, and men that go abroad, and trade by Sea, who buie wares upon Credit; there wil bee continual occaſion of ſuits againſt divers perſons of this ſort, who will not much regard the ſummons, but will betake themſelves, and their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, to Sea again, and the Creditor can have no remedie; whereas if the parties maie bee Attached, they wil make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Whereas divers tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſubſiſt upon their Credits, and take up great ſummes of Monie, for which they can give no other ſecuritie then their
<pb facs="tcp:100047:10"/>perſons, and by advantage thereof, manie times attein to great estates; but if the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of arreſt bee taken awaie, they can hope no more to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, which apparentlie tend's to their ruine.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> And that proceedings by Arreſt maie not ſeem at all cruel, or unjuſt; woe find both preſidents, and approbation of the like, and greater ſeveritie in the Old and New Teſtament; as ſelling the Debtor, his wife and children, and all that hee had to make paiment, and of taking, and caſting into priſon for debt, until the utmoſt farthing were paid: And yet this courſ was not condemn'd amongst the <hi>Romanes,</hi> (ſo much they loved
<pb facs="tcp:100047:10"/>Juſtice) nor by Chriſt himſelf in the New Teſtament, who bid's agree with thy adverſarie before thou com to the Judg: And God, who will have that which is right to be don among men, was verie careful that his own people ſhould paie their debts; and therefore if anie were indebted, though they were poor, and could not paie, yet the Creditor might take the Debtor, and his Children to bee his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and bond-men; and might take their Garments from them, and the bedding whereon they did lie, from under them, which was a far greater puniſhment then our light Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts; for the Priſon, with us, is but a gage, or pledg, until
<pb facs="tcp:100047:11"/>the defendant take courſ to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Action. <hi>Mat. 5.25. Mat. 18.30. 2 Kings 4.7. Levit. 25.39. Prov. 20.16. Prov. 22.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> Men ordinarilie begin Suits upon neceſsitie, and Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors generallie are called upon before anie ſuit is commenced: which indeed is in the nature of a ſummons; but yet neither this, nor the writ of ſummons doth drive men to take anie courſ, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the proceſs of Arreſt iſſue forth, being more compulſorie, and a more ſpeedie remedie for the Creditor, then the milde, and gentle ſummons was found to bee, (as appear's by ſundrie Statutes, <hi>19 Hen. 7. cap. 9.</hi>) which are more proviſional for
<pb facs="tcp:100047:11"/>the Creditor, who is alwaies out of his monie, then for the Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who ſeldom well ſpent it, or hath care to repaie it.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10.</hi> And if by anie new waie, upon meer ſummons onlie, and default, Judgment ſhall bee had before appearance, (which courſ the Law doth not countenance) then the grand pillar of our Common Law, the Trial by <hi>12.</hi> Men (which the Law doth much honor and favor) will fall to the ground; for much buſineſs will reſt whollie upon the Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>david of a ſummoner, or the like, which will bee a means to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie ſuits, and is an unſure courſ, and will induce more perjurie into this Nation, then our Law would ever before this time
<pb facs="tcp:100047:12"/>give an inlett unto: And therefore former Parlaments providing against delaies by ſummons, did not give Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon default, but found out a ſpeedie remedie by Arreſt to bring the Defendant to his anſwer.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11.</hi> By the Law <hi>a Capias ad ſatisfaciendum,</hi> doth not lie, but where there is <hi>a Capias ad ſatisfaciendum</hi> firſt: and there is as great reaſon and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie for the Arreſt to anſwer before Judgment, as for the Arrest to ſatisfie after Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſ the <hi>Capias ad reſpondend.</hi> doth compel the defendant to take notice of the action, to which hee maie plead, if hee will, and doth ſecure him
<pb facs="tcp:100047:12"/>him that hee ſhall not ſtart, ſo that when the Capias <hi>ad ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faciendum</hi> doth iſſue forth, there is left no color of juſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception for the defendant: but on the other ſide, if Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall bee entred upon a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſummons, there will bee manie grievous complaints, and the ſucceeding evils will hardlie bee redreſſed; manie will bee undon, and ſuits will bee multiplied.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12.</hi> Experience doth ſhew that the benefit of the proceſs of Arreſt hath been verie great to this Common wealth: and all the Statutes have mentioned it from time to time, and have given a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger extent unto it, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:100047:13"/>it had, and none have abridged it in anie thing, which is now of great anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, having been for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Ages the beſt remedie (for the People to recover their Debts, and to compoſe other differences) that our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors could deviſe. <hi>Anno Dom. 1267, 1350.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13.</hi> Laſtlie, The ſubtiltie and ſubterfuges of Debtors having made the proceſs of Arreſt now more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie then formerlie, there will be reaſon rather to add to the remedies provided for the Creditors in former Parlaments, then to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them: And if a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencie by this ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb facs="tcp:100047:13"/>a courſ happen to the Debtor, yet will the taking it await prove more preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the Plaintiff, who is the partie inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and in reaſon his caſe to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:14"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100047:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> CRIE <hi>of</hi> BLOUD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt part of this Preamble is far from the matter: Wee confeſs, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts by <hi>Capias,</hi> without Summons, for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Murthers, Felonies, and Treſpaſſes, don <hi>Vi &amp; Armis,</hi> or <hi>Contrapacem,</hi> or <hi>Formam Statuti,</hi> as Extortions, and all Frauds, and Injuſtice, don under color of Office and Juſtice, to bee lawful, and as antient as the Common Law of this Land; and more antient too, becauſ ſuch offences were committed before
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100047:15"/>the Laws were written, or made in thoſe caſes, or thought upon, upon, to puniſh the paſt, and prevent the future. By the Law, wee know the ſin that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; and by the due courſ of Law, the courſ of ſin ought to bee ſtaied or corrected. But what is this to a debtor, which groweth neither <hi>vi &amp; Armis,</hi> nor <hi>contra Pacem,</hi> nor <hi>contra Formam Statuti?</hi> for recoverie whereof, againſt able debtors, the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. And the Common Law before that, provided remedies, the proceſs, or proceedings whereof were by ſummons, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment &amp; diſtreſs, (as our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries confeſs) which courſ, if Antiquitie can meliorate, is far antienter then the <hi>Capias</hi> for debt, which they make no elder then the repealed Statute that gave it, 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.17. which the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100047:15"/>ſame King annulled the 3. and 17. years next after, <hi>viz.</hi> 28. and 42. of his Reign. The delato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs alleged in the courſ of Summons, is a deceitful infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and an untrue report made to the High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament; which were it to an inferior Judicature, deſerveth no leſs puniſhment, then the Informers, to bee impriſoned a year, ſilenced for ever, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ranſomed at the State's pleaſure, <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 29.3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. For the truth is, there can bee no ſpeedier waie deviſed, conſidering Actions of Debt by Common Law, and many Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, ought to bee laid in the proper Countie wherein the Defendant dwelleth, and hath, or hath not wherewith to paie; where the Sheriff having his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, which is the onely proper writ for debt, is a Commiſſion to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100047:16"/>hold plea above fortie ſhillings, and is to ſummon, attach, and diſtrein, and do execution ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the verdict of the Jurie, if in an Hundred Court, in three weeks, allowing fifteen daies, as Law requireth, between Proceſs and Proceſs; which three weeks between Court and Court, may fully afford, and that is no long delaie, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of what is uſual at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> or if in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Court, three moneths, or twelv weeks doth the ſame. But if the Action bee laid in, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to the <hi>Common Pleas</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> (which ought not to bee don, or ſuffered, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out injuſtice, or partialitie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, not alleged in the Sheriff) they cannot determine the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under three Terms, which is not the fault of the courſ of Summóns, which requireth but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100047:16"/>fifteen daies between Proceſs and Proceſs; but the fault (more then delatorie) of the courſ at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which requireth long Vacations between Term and Term, and removeth more Cauſes thither in one Term, or Vacation, then they can end in ſeven.</p>
            <p>And where they ſaie, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons are many times fruitleſs; that is never, except the Debtor hath nothing to bee ſummoned by, &amp; ſo ought not by any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Law, to bee looked after, but with eies of charitie. And why Merchandiſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce in this Nation ſhould bee hindered for want of a <hi>Capias,</hi> to arreſt and impriſon non-ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents to death, cannot bee tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated by any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reaſon, ſince all men know, that all other Nations as well Heathens, as Chriſtians, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100047:17"/>never admitted ſo impious a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie to recover debts, as the <hi>Capias,</hi> finde no hinderance of Trade or Commerce amongſt them, but onely the Trade of Lawyers and Liers, whereof the fewer make the better Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>That former Parlaments pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the <hi>Capias</hi> for debts, as a full and moſt neceſſarie remedie for this Common-wealth; and that divers Statutes affirm ſo much, appeareth to bee theſe men's additions to their former miſ-informations, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, to abuſe this Honorable Parlament: For it was but one Statute that ever provided this <hi>Capias,</hi> and that is long ſince repealed as aforeſaid, and ſo continueth by more then thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie three Parlaments and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. Neither doth that Statute ſhew any cauſ for its proviſion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100047:17"/>making, beeing, or neceſſitie of its continuance, or hath any Preamble at all (as all neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Introductions of Law uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have) but pinneth it ſelf to the Statute made for Accompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, <hi>viz.</hi> Lords, Bailiffs, Rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatherers, and ſervants, that cheated their Maſters of their rents, and monies committed to their truſt, to collect and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for, contrarie to all Laws, Juſtice, Equitie, Mercie, and common honeſtie; all which they falſified, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Maſter's monies to their own uſe; which to anſwer unto by due courſ of Law, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly durſt not abide, for ſhame, more then for the debt, and therefore became Fugitives from their acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: ſo that the <hi>Capias</hi> was neceſſarie to ſtaie, and fetch them to accompt with their Maſters.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100047:18"/>But this pinning, or relating this Statute to that, ſeemeth to bee (as Maſter <hi>Cook</hi> writeth thereof) the work of ſom cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Lawyers, Members of that Parlament, that paſſed it unexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, except by a Committee, which they over-ruled; and that is in a few words, ſo hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled up amongſt other things, as they might bee as ſoon forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the hearers, as read by the Impoſtors: which practiſe they have uſed for the unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable advantage in all Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that truſted them; God bleſs this from the like, and grant it bee not too late wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Howſoëver, that venerable Judge, and Autor of the <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Juſtice, pag.</hi> 283. <hi>ca.</hi> 5. <hi>ſect.</hi> 7. condemneth this <hi>Capias,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth it to bee contrarie to Law; and ſheweth reaſons therefore, both there, and <hi>p.</hi> 108.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100047:18"/>where the Action for accompt is debated, and declared to bee mixt, in regard of the truſt and deceit of the Accomptant, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving therefore to bee proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo far, as to bee forced to an accompt: but for the debt, more then hee hath wherewith to ſatisfie, the Law requireth nothing of him that hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and giveth no recoverie, nor other remedie then revenge, which God calleth his own. And both this Author, and the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> in the <hi>Third part of his Inſtitutes,</hi> agree, that the acting and mainteining of things contrarie to Law, as Law, or lawful, is a ſubverſion of the Law, and that is no leſs then High Treaſon againſt this State and Common-wealth; which caſe is our adverſaries, whom wee hereby impeach thereof, and crave direction and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100047:19"/>aſsiſtance, to indict and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them according to the known Laws in that behalf; So far as they may not loſe the honor of their Antiquitie, which they preſs ſo much for; and wee confeſs, that for the myſteries of its craft, it hath exceeded the Sciences of all their Progenitors in their ſeveral fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; for in the art of men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catching, there are of them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one, who exceed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Three Bum-Bailies, who by virtue of their <hi>Capias,</hi> can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly catch but one by the poll at once, nor that without <hi>vi &amp; Armis,</hi> and loſs, or hazard of lives, by the furie of their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, while our Chamber-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer can make threeſcore <hi>Capiſes</hi> to catch five times threeſcore perſons without any danger of his own, except by the wrath of God, which few of them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100047:19"/>ever feared, but are all embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his patience, to attempt the catching of a whole Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament of moſt wiſe Senators at once, to becom ſubject in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, or their poſterities, to this Purſ-net, perſwading them to father, and maintein this Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard <hi>Capias,</hi> which knoweth no difference between a Parlament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and another, or between his friend and his foe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Art of Ambition, they exceed their Father the Devil, who did but attempt to bee Lord of Hoſts, whilſt theſe men becom Hoſts of Lords, and ſtill covet to enlarge their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the Art of Murthering, they exceed their brother <hi>Cain,</hi> who killed but one <hi>Abel</hi> in all his life time, and for that one offence, had the curſ of God upon him and his ſeed for ever;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100047:20"/>while theſe men daily murther many of their brethren with falſ Judgments, and ſolace themſelves with Angels, deſile their hands, and fill them with bloud, yet would bee heard in Parlament, when God telleth them hee will not hear them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15. and bid's them fill up the meaſure of their Fathers, that upon them may com all the righteous bloud of the Earth, from the bloud of <hi>Abel,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.32.35. and <hi>Luke</hi> 11.50, 51. concluding <hi>v.</hi> 52. <hi>Wo unto you Lawyers, for you have taken away the key of knowledg; you entred not in your ſelves, and them that were entring in, you hindered:</hi> Which Scripture, wee conceiv, may bee fitly applied to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lawyers, who have taken away the Engliſh of our Laws, which was the key of our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg therein; And entred not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100047:20"/>into the truth thereof them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs; and them that would, they hindered, until this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Parlament righted us in that, ſore againſt their wils, and will as wee hope, and they fear, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther right and free us from their bondage, finding that now they have filled the meaſure of their Fathers, that upon them may com, and from them may bee required all the righteous bloud of priſoners for debt, from the bloud of the firſt Free-man of <hi>England,</hi> impriſoned for that cauſ, to the bloud of the laſt that ſhall periſh in priſon for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the Art of Treaſon, they exceed <hi>Judas,</hi> who with one kiſs, betraied but one Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to a death fore-ordeined by God's Providence, for the life of the world, except his deſperate betraier, and other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believer's
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100047:21"/>children of perdition; while theſe men by their daily prevarication, and changing their notes, ſince they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted the Canonical Organs, and Pſalmiſtical Harmonies, to the tune of the Organical Canons, ſhrill Trumpets, and ratling Drums, ſiding with the ſtrongeſt Faction in Warrs, as with the richeſt partie in Peace, till they have betraied three Common-wealths to manifold deaths, avoidable by the mercie of God, and Praiers of men, except theſe impenitents that harden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their wickedneſs, do ſtir up others to ſecond them of ſeditious and implacable ſpirits, ſons of <hi>Belial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. In the art of Impoſtors, they exceed the Pope, and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> who by their impoſtures endeavored but to counterfeit Chriſt's Miracles, and make thoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100047:21"/>counterfeits ſailable at high rates, thereby to diſeſtimate his truth, and prefer their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and to eclipſ his kingdom of grace, that they might oſtentate themſelves in too of Vain glorie; whilſt theſe men having diſguiſed our Lawes in Forraign languages, made them vendible to our ſelves at their own prices, and thereby have ſubjected the ſeven liberal Sciences, and three free King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's of ſeveral free Nations, to their unlimitable impudence, which being over-ruled for the language they intend to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and augment in price and juriſdiction, and ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in one tyrannical Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, as arbitrarie, as intolerable, and as ſlaviſh, as mercinarie. And contrarie to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and were ever ſince the Court called the Upper Bench, hath impoſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100047:22"/>its judicature in matters of Debt, and other Common Pleas, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſlie forbidden them, and taken out of their juriſdiction; and both it, and the Common Pleas, impoſe their Judicature in caſes of Tithes, expreſlie taken out of their juriſdiction by ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and given to the ſpiritual Courts, which (though now ſuppreſſed) their juriſdiction ought not to bee reſumed but by the Parlament, nor executed without an Act for that end.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In the Art of Perjurie; they infinitelie exceed <hi>Peter,</hi> who forſwore himſelf but once, and when he heard the Cock crow, went out from the Maid that urged him, wept bitterlie, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him of his ſin, and reſolved to do ſo no more: whilſt theſe men forſwear themſelves dailie; and when they hear their Pockets ring, go in to their Wenches,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100047:22"/>with whom they interchange deceitful imbraces, and ſeem to laugh merrilie, perſevere in their wickedneſs, and implore a Parlament to countenance, and continue them in condition to do ſo ſtill.</p>
            <p n="7">7, 8, &amp; 9. In the ſeveral Arts of Extortion. Bribing, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication, they exceed the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Judges, <hi>De'Burgo Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilian, Bremble, Thorpe, &amp;c.</hi> as well in their takings, as in their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; for as thoſe were few to their manie, and <hi>Thorp's</hi> taking was but 100 l. from manie hands; how manie hundred pounds taketh one of them from one hand? wee can witneſs too well, and others may compute by the increaſ of the price of an <hi>habeas Corpus,</hi> Error, &amp;c. And the neceſſitie of divers parties to make frequent uſes thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, more to avoid Juſtice.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100047:23"/>them to deſire it: whereby the prevarication, Ambodexterſhip, and Legerdemain of theſe men dailie appeareth more and more by their impairing of their Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents to improve themſelves; manie men of manie thouſands beeing brought ſuddenlie to nothing, and moſt of them from nothing to manie thouſands <hi>per annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. In the Art of Communta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they exceed both Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, and Civilians, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muted corporal penances to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniarie, paiable out of perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal eſtates, while theſe men change Treaſons to treſpaſſes, and Treſpaſſes to treaſons at their pleaſure, and make debt guiltie of death, ſurer, though ſomtimes ſlower then Treaſon, or Miſdemeanor whatſoever, and men's eſtates as well real, as perſonal whollie their own.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In the Art of Transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100047:23"/>they exceed Chamelions, who can bee of anie colour but white, expreſſed in Scripture to bee the immaculate inveſtiture of Angels: Theſe men can ſeem of all colours to ſuit with all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominations, though never ſo divers, and all contraries, and turn the Law for all their turns, and arrogate moſt truſt when they are moſt treacherous, and face themſelves with the truth of Saints, when they are as falſ as Devils.</p>
            <p n="12">12. In the Art of Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting, they exceed both Alchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, and Coyners, of whom the firſt counterfeit, but Gold, and Silver, and turn more Gold to braſs, and Silver to lead, then Copper to Gold, or Lead to Silver: And the ſecond Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, but Pictures, whilſt theſe men counterfeit Juſtice, Equitie, and Lawes, more concernable
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100047:24"/>then Metals, to God and Man; and fix mens ſubſtances, more conſiderable then their pictures, upon themſelves, and their heirs.</p>
            <p n="13">13, &amp; 14. In the Arts of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, and Fraud, they exceed all Coiners of falſ Monies, and Counterfeiters of Letters, and Tokens; whom, if they catch with ſuch miſdeameanors, they ſomtimes ſeverelie puniſh, and ſomtimes paſs over ſleightlie, or excuſe artificiallie, as may moſt conduce to their profit, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with their practiſe, whilſt they themſelvs make it a chief part of their office to forge the returns of Sheriffs and Coroners of ſeveral Writs, and to file them for true Records, and due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of Law; whereupon follow Judgments, Executions, and Impriſonments to manie thouſands, to their utter undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100047:24"/>and for want of ſummons, Attachments, and exigents dulie executed, and returned by thoſe Officers who never ſee them, yet are anſwerable by Law for thoſe falſ Returns made unknown to them, and the Forgers thereof, as of all other faudulent deeds which cannot be drawn, ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, antedated, and contrived adviſedlie without them, or ſom of their Counſels, ought to bee puniſhed for the ſame, for which they are never queſtioned; but contracting the greateſt Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, wherein they are actors, paſs for good deeds and online thoſe trifles that want their skill, and privitie, are made great, or dear offences.</p>
            <p n="15">15. In the Art of Lying they exceed the men of <hi>Creet,</hi> and <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeba,</hi> who (as is written, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.22.) were alſo Ancient, as theſe men would be accompted;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100047:25"/>for thoſe but as Men and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, lied but to men in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things, whilſt theſe men, as Devils, lie unto God, and in contempt of his Divine Word, and Deitie, as ſhall appear here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p n="16">16. In the art of Simonie, they exceed <hi>Simon</hi> himſelf, who would have bought, for his monie, the Gifts of the Holie Ghoſt, and intending the Apoſtles fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, purchaſed their indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: whilſt theſe men have, with their Monie's, purchaſed their Offices, and all the ſaid gifts of the Devil, to execute them, and by the ſame endeavor to acquire the favor of manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corrupt members, who (as wee hope) ſhall not bee ſuffered long to abuſe the reſt of this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Parlament.</p>
            <p n="17">17. and 18. In the arts of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, and Tenacitie, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100047:25"/>Catchpols and Gaolers exceed Lions, and Tygers, and their Gaols and Dungeons Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yen, and Hell, for Lions will favor their friends, and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers their neighbors. And Heaven wll neither take, nor receiv, anie but God's Elect; nor Hell anie but Reprobates; but Catchpols, Goalers, and their Gaols catch, and receiv all men they can ſue, and count all too few, and keep them in their pawes, and caves, while they are worth a farething.</p>
            <p>And thus having ſuppedinated their Proëm with eighteen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of their properties that appropriate to themſelvs all our proprieties, and ſo ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerated their 13 falſ Reaſons for the ſupportation of their innumerable falſities, wee ſhall deſcend to fiſt thoſe Reaſons as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100047:26"/>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is all falſ; for the attaching of perſons ſecureth no part of the Plaintiffs debts by paiment, or other ſatisfaction, but commonly their debtors bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to miſerable deaths, and their eſtates from their heirs and creditors, to Lawyers and Officers: For the proceedings by Summons, wee have anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before. And for Priſoners that are able to give for their libertie or their Gaolers, they have as much as they deſire and paie for out of their creditors rights; and their own Frie, and not the Plaintiffs, or their heirs, have their Gaoler's leavings.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is like the firſt; for it is not a few, that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined for debt, when Sir <hi>Jo. Len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hal</hi> hath in his cuſtodie or liſt one thouſand perſons; the Warden of the <hi>Fleet</hi> as many, the Gaols of <hi>London, Weſtminiſter,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100047:26"/>and Liberties adjoining, few leſs; and in the reſt of all the Gaols of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> will bee found many more. They that accompt ſo many few, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their deſire is to have all the Free-men of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> (except themſelves) in the ſame caſe; why? and with whom elſ do they make the compariſon, but becauſ they conveiv there are more perſons out of priſon, then in; their detention is not ſeldom, but frequent, and ſo are murthers, and hurts, committed as well before, and at, as after arreſts; by reaſon thereof, they are not deteined for a ſhort time, but ordinarily till death as aforeſaid: Warrant of Atturnie, if they need any Atturnies, they ought to give to whom they pleaſ, and not to whom any Court appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. And for appearance, no
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100047:27"/>Free-man oweth it to any Court out of his Decenarie, Hundred, or Countie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is but a block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head-ſhip's Proëm, as untrue as the former, and ſo demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our anſwer thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. No Trade but Lawyers, nor ſuch, but <hi>Weſtmonasterians,</hi> will bee hindered by taking away the <hi>Capias.</hi> It was the lawleſs uſe thereof, that cauſed more Uſurers then Merchants, to look after men's perſons: It ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was, nor could bee the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt waie for Plaintiffs to gain their debts, but the moſt dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie to recover, and the moſt readie and uſual to loſe them; ſo as the repetition of the decaie of Trade, if the <hi>Capias</hi> were taken off, is but tautologie for want of reaſon, and an abuſe of Parlament, to bee offered ſuch untruths, to hear, or look
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100047:27"/>upon, puniſhable as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth is as bad as all the former; for the attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a man's perſon, where he hath neither means to paie, nor friends to bail, produceth no end but Impriſonment, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and Attachments of men's goods, where they have to paie, conduce to the ſpeedieſt end between Debtor and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor: Hee that hath of his own to paie, will regard Summons, leſt if that hee bee attached, hee ſhall loſe all, and if ſubmitted to his Creditor's mercie, hee may ſave ſom. Hee that hath enough, or more then ſufficient to paie his Creditors, of his own eſtate, will neither regard Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, nor fear Arreſt, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, beeing ſure of what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie hee pleaſeth, paying his Gaoler, and to leav what his Gaoler leaveth, to whom hee
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100047:28"/>liſt, as aforeſaid; whereby more Creditors are cheated, then by any other deceit, and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, then debtors of that kinde, who commonly live too plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and leav ſomthing, when their Creditors have nothing whereby to live, or whereof to leav.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth is as untrue as the reſt; for a debtor that is worth the Summoning, can live no where better then in his Decenarie where hee is beſt known, and hath his pledges anſwerable for his honeſtie; nor can hee tranſfer his eſtate to any other Countie but to his loſs: And his avoiding the due courſ of Law, is a miſdemeanor that depriveth him of the benefit depriveth him of the benefit thereof; which beeing certified by a <hi>Testatum,</hi> a <hi>Capias</hi> of courſ enſueth, to purſue him from Countie to Countie, till hee bee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100047:28"/>found, or outlawed; which was ever lawful againſt ſuch as waved their Law and freedom, to anſer it in its due courſ; and ſuch a Certificate of the Sheriff of that Countie whence hee fled, ought to make to the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie,</hi> whence hee had his Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to determine the matter; and the <hi>Chancerie</hi> ought to ſend the <hi>Capias</hi> to the Sheriff in whoſe Countie hee doth <hi>latitare, &amp; diſcurrere;</hi> and ſo the <hi>alias Plures, Exigent,</hi> and Outlawrie, till hee bee forced to return him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the firſt Sheriffs, to have his cauſ determined there by his Peers, as it ought: all which, affording fifteen daies between Proceſs and Proceſs, is feaſible in half a year; and what hee ſhall bee then found to have left of his perſonal eſtate, his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors muſt have all, and two parts of his real; with leſs then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100047:29"/>a tenth part of the fees and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies uſed at <hi>Westminſter:</hi> which old courſ of Law beeing reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſo known, will make everie able debtor ſubmit to Summons, and farther Proceſs, eſpecially Outlawries, more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and odious then now, when they are but ſcare-crows, rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable and extinguiſhable by their grantors, for their gain at their pleaſures: For the debtor that is not worth the ſummoning, up on the Sheriffs return of <hi>Non eſt inventus, &amp; nihil habet,</hi> the Law is ended (as aforeſaid) until God enable him. And in the interim, whereſoëver hee lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or liveth, by lawful endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, <hi>Cantabil vacuus coram la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone viator,</hi> no debtor juſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted, can, or ought to bee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by any juſt law, or equitie to make away his eſtate, before hee paie his juſt debts, for it is not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100047:29"/>his own, but his creditor's; and ſuch Conveiances ought to bee adjudged fraudulent, although the fraudulent makers of that fraudulent Statute, have inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the words <hi>honlifide,</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their imps, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had good faith or honeſtie to expound for their profit, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; for good faith can do no man wrong, but falſ Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer's interpretations thereof, and of the Law, commonly wrong all men, and enrich onely them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The Lord <hi>coke</hi> in the <hi>Third part of his Inſtitutes,</hi> upon the Writ <hi>de odio &amp; atia,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth theſe men to bee lier that charge the Law, or its makers, with more regard of men's debets, then their liberties.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The fixth is of the ſame ſtuff, and in ſubſtance anſwered before. Do more Merchants trade out of <hi>England</hi> by ſea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſ
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100047:30"/>it is an Iſland, then into it out of larger and Forrain lands, where the <hi>Capias</hi> for debt was never known? Do not theſe men buy wares upon truſt, and trade to ſea as often as the Engliſh? and having no <hi>Capias,</hi> have their creditors no Laws to recover their debts? is it not better to attach their debtor's goods, or their, then their bodies? And ſo hath <hi>London</hi> uſed to do by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and other Towns and Ports ought to have don ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel; and the Law of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie hath its courſ of Juſtice within its juriſdiction. Wil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawyers have no Law but their baſtard the <hi>Capias,</hi> to range about by Sea and Land, like its its Grandfather the Devil, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom it may devour? Nay, are not the words of the Writ of Summons, at the Common
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100047:30"/>Law, directed to the Sheriff, which any Major, or chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of any Corporation, may upon complaint direct to Sheriff or Sergeant; <hi>praecipe, &amp;c. per bonos ſummonitores;</hi> that is, I command thee to ſummon <hi>A B,</hi> &amp;c. by good Summonitors, &amp;c. and have their names, &amp;c, and this Writ before mee by ſuch a daie: And to what end? but that the Summonitors beeing two, or more of the ableſt Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or Pledges of the Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, undertaking the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, undertake the goods till the Attachment enſue, if they cannot end the matter before, as neighbors bound in charitie ſo to do. But theſe <hi>Weſtmonaſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> abhor that, and ſeem neither to know, nor willing to admit any charitable end, or other Law, but their <hi>Capias</hi> to catch and bring all fiſh to their net.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100047:31"/>
            <p n="7">7. The ſeventh is but a chip of the ſixth, and anſwered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with this addition. Is there no truſt, but where the <hi>Capias</hi> is, or can thruſt it ſelf? If it bee the cauſ of truſt, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Equitie, &amp;c. and ſuch a cauſ, as without which none of theſe can ſubſiſt (as they ſaie it is) and both legal and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for this Common-wealth, that it ſeem's the onely Truſtee thereof? Why is it not warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or ſuffered by theſe men themſelvs to peep into their Inns of Court, and <hi>Chancerie?</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pretended to bee egreſs and ingreſs of Law, Juſtice and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and known to take upon truſt more then all the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of <hi>England</hi> can tell how to recover by the <hi>Capias</hi> againſt their perſons, who make their Inns, and their Gaols of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Bench, and Fleet their San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuaries,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100047:31"/>more privileged then thoſe that were ſo called and uſed by ſuch debtors as made fraudulent gifts, feoffments, &amp;c. and afterwards withdrew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs thither, untill the ſecond Statute made the ſecond year of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond, granted a <hi>Capias</hi> to ferret out ſuch Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants out of ſuch Latebras; Such a ferret conceiv wee now, to bee neceſſarie for the Common-wealth, and eſpecially for many undon <hi>Londoners,</hi> by truſting ſuch debtors, or rather cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to fetch them out of their profane Aſylums, the <hi>Fleet, Marſhalſey,</hi> their Inns, &amp;c. inſtead of that by them commended for the uſe of the Common-wealth, and yet commanded not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with themſelvs, or their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations; as if they concluded themſelvs and theirs, to bee no part thereof, though will known
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100047:32"/>to bee all forfeited thereunto. But how irrational they ſhew themſelvs, when they offer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to a moſt wiſe and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Parlament, to perſuade them that can onely bee profitable to all, which is ſo unwelcom to them, that they cannot endure their own beagles that carrie it abroad, to bee their Inmates an hour longer then while they ſlave and pump them, and ſo make them as fit to bee their Maſs-Prieſts, as their prolling Proctors.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The eighth ſheweth theſe men's deſires, as well to pervert the Word of God, as to ſubvert the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth their right as well to the Faggot, as to the Halter, and their fitneſs as well for Hell, as the Gallows. They bluſh not to ſaie, that they finde preſidents and approbations in the Old and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100047:32"/>New Teſtaments, of like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and greater cruelties againſt debtors, amongſt the Jews, then is uſed by them and their <hi>Capias</hi> here: And thoſe (ſaie they) were condemned, neither by the Romanes, that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Juſtice, nor by Chriſt. The firſt Scripture they cite, is <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.25. where <hi>whoſoëver is angrie with his brother without a cauſ,</hi> is adviſed <hi>to leav his gift before the Altar, and bee reconciled to his brother firſt, and then offer his gift, leſt at any time the Adverſarie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him to the Judg, and the Judge deliver him to the Officer, and hee bee caſt into priſon;</hi> where Chriſt ſaith unto him, <hi>Verily, I ſaie unto thee, thou ſhalt by no means com out, until thou paieſt the utter most farthing:</hi> wherewith agreeth <hi>Lu.</hi> 12.58.59. and both with the Parable of the non-ſolvent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.25. &amp; all theſe places
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100047:33"/>conclude with the reſt of the Scriptures, that the debt here meant to bee puniſhed by impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, was not a debt of monie borrowed for need, and lent for love, propheſied to bee don. <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.6. and commanded <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and 42. And therefore beeing no action of ſin by the Old and New Teſtament, was liable to no action of Law, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to perſonal puniſhment or impriſonment; but the debt meant here, was indeed the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Uſurer, Extorter, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, Hypocrite, &amp;c. to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give their debtors their debts ſo accrued: But Uſurie, Extortion, Briberie, &amp;c. which were ſuch heinous offences amongſt the Jews, as ſtill they are, or ought to bee with us, that they incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mixt actions in Law wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of arreſts and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, till the uttermoſt farthing
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100047:33"/>were paied, or reſtored, with amends; <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.2, 3, <hi>&amp;</hi> 4, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth this debt to bee ſuch cleerly, and no other. Our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws for thoſe offences, which make the principal debts void, and give the Plaintiff tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for damages, or according to the Judge's diſcretion, carrie ſhadow of that Juſtice. The Context in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our Savior's ſpeeches to the Scribes and Phariſees, elſwhere called Lawyers, Extorters, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, &amp;c. and here redargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their unrighteouſneſs, and breaking of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which they adjudged death to others; accompting killing onely ſuch as was don with the ſword, and him to bee ſubject to the judgment, where they knew; that by their own law, men that killed in their own defence, had ſanctuarie, &amp; that the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100047:34"/>word Judgment emphatically proceeded with the word The, is always uſed for the general Judgment of God: wherefore Chriſt telling them, that killing extend's to him that is angrie with his brother without cauſ, and elſwhere to him that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his brother to periſh when hee may ſave him; much more then to Falſ Judges, Extorters, Uſurers, &amp;c. who may finde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſufficientlie deſcribed in him to whom his Lord forgave all his debt; (which in the laſt verſ of this Chapter (as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentlie elſwhere) is called as well treſpaſs, as debt, becauſ mixt, and compounded with ſin, more then borrowing, or lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of monie) until hee extorted from his fellow-ſervant, who ought nothing to him, but to his Lord, upon whom he had not like compaſſion, as his Lord
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100047:34"/>had upon himſelf, but grew an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie with his fellow-ſervant without cauſ, and caſt him into priſon; which, when his Lord heard, he was wroth, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the mad Extortor, not the meek Debtor to the tormenter, &amp;c whereof let Extorters, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, &amp;c. take better notice, and applie the ſaid Scriptures to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emſelvs, and know that the Devil, called here emphaticallie the Adverſarie, is he that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth them (as the common accuſer of ſinners whom hee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth thereunto) to the Judg of Judges, and King of Kings, the God of Truth, Juſtice, and Mercie, who (except they ſay, and reſolv to pay all, <hi>viz.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and have like compaſſion upon their brethren, as they expect from him) will deliver them to the Officer, as ſaith <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> the 5. Tormentor, as ſaith
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100047:35"/>
               <hi>Matthew</hi> 18. <hi>viz.</hi> the Devil again, who ſupplieth all ſuch offices, and delivereth all that are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to him, to Hell, whence is no Redemption, till the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing bee paid, which is never to be don after the oil is out of the lamp, and the dore ſhut: Where contrariwiſe the Law of the Jews (which Chriſt ſaith hee came not to deſtroie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17. and neither did, nor would alter, as appeareth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.25.) did not impriſon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie debtors at all, but ſell them, and their wives and children, and all they had to their credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that were bound by the ſame law to keep, and finde them in their houſes, and imploiments, not in priſons, and dungeons, without, and from all imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but wickedneſs, as our Gaolers do us; nor as theſe men impiouſlie allege, and belie the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100047:35"/>Holie Ghoſt, ſaying, That their creditors might take their deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor's cloaths, and bed-cloaths from them; where the Text they cite, (<hi>Lev.</hi> 25.39.) ſaith, they muſt uſe them as brethren, hired ſervants, and ſojorners (which we finde all the Old Teſtament over, had the truſt, and charge, not onlie of their Maſter's eſtates, but of their children, and their wives, and wanted nothing ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not onlie to their own ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, but alſo to their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's credits, and imployments. And debtors were to be kept ſo by vertue of their ſale, but till the year of Jubilee, which, when it fell within ſeven years in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> reſtored them to their libertie; for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, the ſeventh year they were to be reſtored, as appeareth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.1. &amp;c. And in <hi>Jeremie's</hi> time, at the fixth years end, <hi>Jer.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100047:36"/>34.14. Now doth the Capias, Arreſts, and Impriſonments uſed by theſe men, hold anie analogie with the mercie, juſtice, ſuſten. ſtentation, freedom, and hope of libertie in few years, which the Jewiſh law afforded to thoſe debtors they ſold to their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors? Compare, and finde as followeth: There the debtors had the mercie to be no Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners at all, but as hired ſervants, and ſojorners: The Juſtice, to bee no bondmen which maſters might uſe at their pleaſures: The ſuſtentation; to have food and raiment enough, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent to their conditions, and their maſters callings: The freedom; to live, and love huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, wives, and children all together; to pray, feed ſheep, and work comfortablie together in their maſters houſes, fields, vine yards, &amp;c. with no leſs good
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100047:36"/>inſtruction, and recreätion to themſelves, then profit and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their maſters, and hope of full libertie to make uſe of thoſe good inſtruments for their own beſt advange at ſix years end, if a Jubilee freed them no ſooner. Contrariewiſe; here the pooreſt debtor hath the cruelleſt impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment; that is the rule of theſe men's mercie: The greateſt cheater hath the greateſt favor; that is their Juſtice: The ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wee would buy for our ſelvs at the beſt hand, while our monie laſt's, our Goalers take, or keep from us, to force us to buy half ſo much, and nothing ſo good of them, while wee have a pennie left; and after to ſtarve; when others, for our Cuſtom, would prolong our lives, with truſt for a time, they will truſt no poor man for a farthing; nor rich, but to fetch his monie. Our Freedom is not to the next
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100047:37"/>Ward, nor in our own, to enjoy wives, or children, longer then they bring fees to the Gaoler; that when we have ſold our cloaths, and bed-cloaths to feed our bloud-ſuckers, our common bed is the bare ground, till wee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh here, and our wives and children in the ſtreets, and dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, do the like; hope of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wee have none, but by ſuch deaths; for our livelihoods are too little to pay our Fees from the dayes of our Arreſts, to our Funeral: if anie attein to liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by ſome caſualtie, hee is the worſ while hee liveth for his Gaol education. Our Law is derived from the <hi>Romanes,</hi> who (as theſe men ſay) condemned not the Law of the Jewes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Creditors, and Debtors; wee wiſh ours were as merciful; and ſo it was before and ſince <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> when it medled not with men's bodies that had
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100047:37"/>not wherewith to pay their debts, but relieved, and imploied them according to their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, forgiving their debts, and believing that of our Savior; if you forgive not men's treſpaſſes, neither will my Father forgive yours, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. But theſe men that dare abuſe the everlaſting Word of the everliving God, and the fundamental Laws of this Land grounded thereupon, to miſ-inform a Parlament to their own ends, notwithſtanding they know wee have abundance of ſound Divines to expound Scriptures, and ſome honeſt Lawyers, though no profeſſors to explain Lawes. What ſhall wee think of theſe men's ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be truſted with the making up, and keeping of Records con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the whole eſtates of the Common-wealth? but ſubmit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the conſideration thereof to all intereſted therein.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:100047:38"/>
            <p>Their 9. Reaſon purſueth the former in its Coin; for moſt untrue it is, That men alwaies begin ſuits (meaning by way of Capias, and Arreſt) upon neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of injuſtice, that is to ſay; when no other trick will ſerv to bar men of their libertie to proſecute juſt ſuits for loſs of lives, or eſtates of moſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or for Treaſons, felonies, or treſpaſſes moſt notorious, committed by night, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by injuſtice, what is more common then to arreſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors for ſuppoſed debts of thouſands of pounds, more then they are able to find bail for, until Trials, and Judgments bee carried againſt them in the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they ſhould follow by the ſame hands of Power and Juſtice, that they ſhould proſecute, but cannot, being ſo prevented. And how manie are now impriſoned for ſuppoſed debts, which they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100047:38"/>never ought, or if they did, have paid, or which were not due at the time of the Arreſt, &amp;c. And what neceſſitie of Juſtice was to begin ſuch ſuits? And what murther more wilful, more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and more cruel, then to impriſon men ſo till they die? And where they ſay, that moſt commonlie debtors have notice before any ſuit be commenced, why then do they debar ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which is the right proceſs of notice? How come Juſtices of Peace, and Grand Jurie men, that alwaies attend Aſſizes and and Seſſions, to be arreſted by bills of middle Latitats, and Outlawries, before they can hear of anie ſuits againſt them? which caſe is common. And for their alleging of manie Statutes, or Parlaments, that approved of their Capias, let them name one more then that of 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.17. which gave it, and was repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100047:39"/>28 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.3. and 42 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. as aforeſaid. What Statute, or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, ever ſince revived it in expreſs terms? It is true, That of 19 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.9. ordeineth proceſs upon Actions of treſpaſs upon the caſe to bee no more delatorie then that practiſed for debt. And wee grant that actions upon the Caſe, being mixt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ever ought to have been by Capias before that Statute, however neglected by ſuch as ever left undon thoſe things which they ought to have don, to do thoſe things which they ought not. And that ſummons is a milder way, and not ſo compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorie: as the Capias, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and hold more Chriſtian; for the Capias compelleth men that are not able to pay their debts, and that never ought anie, to be impriſoned, ſtarved, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered: And no juſt debt to bee paid ſo ſoon as ſummons, all the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100047:39"/>world knoweth thereof, and therefore no Nation but <hi>Engliſh</hi> admitteth a Capias for debt.</p>
            <p>The 10. is as deceitful an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation as anie before that; for wee deſire no new way upon ſummons, to haſten Judgments before Attachments and diſtreſs, by affidavit of a ſummoner: but that ſummons may go by Writ, as it was wont, to the Sheriff of the Countie wherein the debtor dwelleth, requiring him by good ſummonitors (which are the words of the Writ) to ſummon the partie to bee at the return of the Writ, in the Court whence it iſſued, whether the Sheriff is to return both the writ, and the ſummonitor's names, in that ought to be ſubſtantial free-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and free pledges of the ſame decenarie as the debtor, who, if they return <hi>ſummonitus,</hi> are anſwerable for ſo much as they finde him worth, till At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100047:40"/>taketh it into the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff's hands, or ſureties for appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. If the return bee a <hi>nibil haber,</hi> then (as aforeſaid) the Law ought to look no further after him, till God make him able: for (as the Proverb was) where nothing was to be had, the King was to looſ his due. And if the return bee <hi>non est inventus,</hi> his ſhunning of the Law maketh him a malefactor, ſubject to a Capias upon a <hi>Teſtatum</hi> directable to the Sheriff of the Countie wherein he lurketh, and ſo from Countie to Countie, till hee bee taken, or out-lawed. Again, if the return be <hi>ſummonitus,</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment, diſtreſs, and Judgment follow of courſ, legallie, and ſpeedilie, and are the onlie due proceſs of Law, as wee have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared before; and ſo is not a Judgment by <hi>nihil dicit,</hi> ſtolne by connivence of Attornies, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the Defendant, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100047:40"/>his warrant of Attornie bee had to appear for him: a common feat countenanced too much by the Law at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to thouſands undoings, and their own gain. For trial by Jurie, Iſſues joined, cannot bee tried o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, <hi>Nihil dicits,</hi> &amp; Arreſts by <hi>Capias</hi> uſe them not: For mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicitie of Suits and Perjuries, they were things never found fault with at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> theſe 200 years, till now. And now if the <hi>Chancerie</hi> grant Juſticieſes to Sheriffs and Stewards, as they ought, <hi>gratis;</hi> and Corporations proceed by their Charters, <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaſterians</hi> need not fear to bee troubled with multiplicitie of Suits; and thoſe growing fewer, ſo will their perjuries.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The eleventh is a toie; for wee grant that a <hi>Capias ad reſpondend.</hi> beeing unlawful, that <hi>ad ſatisfaciend.</hi> is groundleſs, and both moſt lawleſs, and uſeleſs;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100047:41"/>the due proceſs of law for debt being as aforeſaid, ſummons, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="12">12. The twelfth is a Riddle and a Paradox, wherewith theſe men would amaze us with ſom wonders of their experience hapned by this Common-wealth by the benefit of their <hi>Capias,</hi> which they call the Proceſs of Arreſt, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1267, <hi>&amp;</hi> 1350. They might have don well to declare their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that others that know them not, might judg thereof as well as themſelves. Wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and they know the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, Impriſonment, Exile, and Hanging of Traitors, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners, &amp;c. as were the <hi>Spencers,</hi> Father and Son; the Judges <hi>Hugh d' Burgo, Treſilian,</hi> &amp;c. who ſeduced Kings, as theſe men would Parlament, were beneficial to this Common-wealth; and wee hope it will bee ſo again, though wee know
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100047:41"/>not how long the Devil may help his ſervants: but of poor debtors wee can remember no arreſt that was ever beneficial to any one perſon of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, but have ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved the Negative.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Laſtly, for the ſubtilties, and ſubterſuges of debtors, wee know none more then theſe men; and their predeceſſors taught ſuch as grew indebted, and by their natural inclinations, aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with theſe men's advices, and devices, far more ſubtle then their own, to cheat men of their Lands and Eſtates; and by the credits of their ſureties, that took them to be honeſt men, until too late, they found the contrarie. Wee confeſs it is true, that ſuch debtors by the helps of ſuch teachers, became ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as to get in their hands all they could of their Creditor's rights, and conveied them to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100047:42"/>what uſes they pleaſed; and procuring themſelvs afterwards to bee arreſted, where they might bee brought, or removed to the upper Bench, or <hi>Fleet;</hi> made thoſe places their ſanctuaries and ſubterfuges, where they are many thouſands in liſt, but few in cuſtodie, riding, rioting, and ſpending their Creditor's and Suretie's Eſtates, ſomtimes at their own doors, who want for their ſakes thoſe bleſſings to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev them, which they vainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to out-brave them; and ſomtimes in parts remote and Forrain, more active againſt this Common-wealth, then for it.</p>
            <p>The premiſes tenderly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and for that theſe men, by theſe their endeavors declare themſelvs, and their Judges, and the reſt of their rabble, to bee of one fraternitie; and all parties in this matter of our wrongful impriſonments, and guiltie of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100047:42"/>all the Extortions and Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concurrent therewith, and livers, and thrivers thereupon; and therefore no fit Judges in theſe cauſes, as further appeareth by their lothneſs to ſubmit, or give waie to the Houſ, whereof they are over-ruling members, to perform their promiſes to your Excellence in our behalfs, made many years paſt, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore us, and themſelvs, to our birth-right, liberties, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, whereof they have robbed us, but are aſhamed ſo to do like thievs and intruders, to deliver their poſſeſſions to the right ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. May it therefore pleaſ your Honor, in our further be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfs, to cauſ the Houſ once more to bee moved to grant a Commiſſion under the Great Seal, directed to indifferent Commiſsioners, that ſhall bee no profeſſed Lawyers, Atturnies, &amp;c. or perſons engaged to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100047:43"/>emploiments, Martial, or Civil; but men of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and diſcretion, undoubted honeſtie, well-affected to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government, to bee nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by us, and approved by any two, or more Parlament-men; autoriſing everie two, or more ſuch Commiſſioners, (not excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding twelv in all) to deliver all the Gaols of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> of all priſoners for debt, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with without delaie, compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all that are able, to paie all or part of their juſt debts, to paie accordingly, ſo far as all their goods, (except the beaſts of their plough, tools of their trade, and neceſſarie cloaths and bedding) and two parts of their Lands ſhall extend, notwithſtanding any Conveiance of any ſuch Lands ſince the debts grew, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept diſtributions between real Creditors.) And to hear and determine all wrongful Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100047:43"/>Extortions, Briberies, Uſuries, Perjuries, Forgeries, Frauds, Deceits, Treſpaſſes, or Oppreſsions whatſoëver, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch priſoners onely, committed, or to bee committed by any perſon or perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoëver, againſt them, or any of them, or by any of them againſt any of their Creditors, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> according to the antient Laws and Cuſtoms of <hi>England,</hi> confirmed by the great Charter, and Petition of Right, to endure for three years from the date thereof; allowing everie ſuch Commiſsioner 300 <abbr>l</abbr> 
               <hi>per annum,</hi> above his neceſſarie expences, for his ſalarie, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his pains, and loſs in his time, and private affairs; and ſuch fees, and allowances to their Clerks, Meſſengers, and other neceſſarie Miniſters, as any three of them ſhall think fit, not exceeding the preſidents
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100047:44"/>of other Courts, in like caſes, to bee deducted out of ſuch fines, amerciaments, iſſues, profits, and perquiſits, as ſhall grow due to the Common-wealth, by their ſervice, as other Courts uſe to do; and the reſt to bee accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for, to ſuch other publick uſes, as the Houſ ſhall appoint: Which beeing don by your means, the Land ſhall bee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of much iniquitie, the Lord's wrath for the ſame much appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, your Excellencie, and your Armie gain much happineſs, love, and honor, divine, and humane, temporal, and eternal; the Common-wealth regain a Million of monie picked out of their purſes by Extorters, Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and common Deceivers; and your Petitioners bee at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to fight for their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and ſafegard of thoſe lives of their own with courage and comfort, which as yet they have
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100047:44"/>no hope but to loſe with care, and ſorrow.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And they, and theirs, as in dutie bound, ſhall ever praie, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="case">
            <head>A Caſe concerning a matter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</head>
            <p>TO the premiſes I muſt add another Caſe of no leſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuitie and manifeſtation of our Lawyer's actions, then the former, briefly thus; A Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Drurie-lane,</hi> ever faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Parlament's ſervice, and an adventurer of his life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes therein, imparted for their uſe and the Common-wealths, 3600 <abbr>l</abbr> readie monie, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to bee repaied, with law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful conſideration, in convenient time, to ſupply his own occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, much ſubject to oppreſsions and injuries offered unto him by Lawyers, and their Clients; in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100047:45"/>which reſpect it pleaſed the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament to take him into their protection, which hee conceiveth Lawyers ſitting Members in the Houſ, adviſed or conſented to bee don, and granted as a lawful and juſt thing; or had it been otherwiſe, would have adviſed the contrarie, and never conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſame. Now the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman (having received none of his monie, nor any conſideration for any part thereof, is forced to borrow monie upon hard terms, of Uſe, and other Engagements, to buie his Leaſes late held of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Elie,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent others to deprive him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, beeing his main ſubſiſtance,) can have no benefit of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, from any of them that granted it, or of thoſe Courts wherein they are imploied, and eminently autoriſed; and the Gentleman and his Eſtate daily and unduly queſtioned, yet deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100047:45"/>hee no more then his own, to defend himſelf from injuſtice, or to bee protected therefrom, until hee hath his own, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice with it, or for it; or that hee may bee ſatisfied how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie it is, or can bee to this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament and Common-wealth, or either to have theſe men, theſe Counſellors, theſe Adviſers, or rather Deviſers of frauds, and ſubtleties to delude Truth and Juſtice, that will counſel, adviſe, deviſe, or conſent things to bee granted, which they will not juſtifie to bee performed by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, (except that as in caſes of common concernment, wherein the partie moſt ſuffering ought to have negation from all) Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemes are tolerable in war, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued or tolerated in place or power, to miſ-guide Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as their predeceſſors have don Kings in times of peace, or to bee ſole Judges or Interpreters
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100047:46"/>of their own inventions; no leſs dangerous to this Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and their Eſtates, then the Expoſition of Papiſtical Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, while it was left to the autors, was to our predeceſſors and their ſouls. All which is humbly ſubmitted to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor's further conſideration, with the reſt as aforeſaid; by the ſame</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honor's faithful ſervant, and obſervant, <hi>Jo. Jones.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="case">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:100047:46"/>
            <head>A Caſe concerning <hi>Tythes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOR the further manifeſtation of the lawleſs Impoſture, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation of Juriſdiction, Arbitrarie proceeding, and deſtruction of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietie, exerciſed daily, and generally by Judges, and no Judges at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and in their Circuits to the deheredetation of many, and hazard of all; may ſummarily appear in that one Caſe lately adjudged by no Judges legally authoriſed thereunto, between Sir <hi>Matth. Liſter</hi> Knight, Plaintiff, and <hi>Lionel Gelſon,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant, publiſhed in print, partly by Petition, partly otherwiſe, by the modeſt and diſcreet wife, and fellow-ſufferer of the Defendant, in the Cauſ of <hi>Ann Gelſon:</hi> the brief whereof is this; the Plaintiff beeing poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Tythes of a Rectorie, called <hi>Burwel,</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> an Impropriation, ſomtimes parcel of the diſſolved College of <hi>Totterial</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:100047:47"/>in the ſaid Countie, by virtue of a Conveiance derived from a Grant of King <hi>H 8.</hi> in which it is mentioned that the ſaid King gave that Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>(cùm pertinentiis inter alia)</hi> to the then Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and his heirs. And becauſ it is there fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mentioned, that the ſaid King gave alſo to the ſaid Duke the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the Rectorie of <hi>Walmſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> which is a Pariſh of it ſelf in another Decenarie, and <hi>Wapentack</hi> of the ſaid Countie, diſtinct from, though neighboring to that of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> and founded by the Lord of the Manor of <hi>Walmſgate,</hi> who then was (as yet the Defendant who clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from him, is) Lord of all that Pariſh in Fee-ſimple, and gave the Tithe thereof (as well his own, as his Tenants at will) to the Rector for the time beeing, and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors for ever, reſerving to himſelf, and his heirs for ever, the Patronage and Preſentation; ſo that when there hapned a neglect of Preſentation in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100047:47"/>him, or in his heirs, the right thereof fell by lapſ to the Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> and upon his neglect, to the King; which beeing ſo then, in King <hi>H. 8.</hi> hee might grant for that time to the ſaid Duke: But ſaving for that time, or the like relapſ, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance deſcended to the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. Now this Inheritance from the Defendant, and Tithes from the Incumbent, and his Farmor, are adjudged to the Plaintiff, by Judges and Jurors, according to the courſ of Common Law, (as they pretend) whereas by the Statute <hi>2 Ed. 6.13.</hi> and many preſidents, no right of Tithes ought to bee tried but by Eccleſiaſtical Judges, and Courts according to Eccleſiaſtical Laws; which, though now aboliſhed, the ſaid Statutes beeing not repealed, the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature is obeied, and yet undiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of by the Parlament, which onely can diſpoſe thereof. But in the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim, ſuch Judges and Jurors, as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume juriſdiction to trie the rights of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100047:48"/>Tythes by Common Law, are no Judges, but offendors in <hi>Premunire;</hi> ſuch trials, no trials, but arbitrarie and lawleſs Diſſeiſins, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of men's properties; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently (if not timely remedied) of the common libertie, rights, and birth-rights of all the Commonaltie of <hi>England;</hi> And the Defendant can but fear to bee deprived by the ſame courſ, of his whole Manor, and ſubſiſtence, as well as hee is of part.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100047:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
